בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is עין א, Ayin Alef,
71. We pick up at the bottom of עין עמוד ב Ayin
Amud Bet and actually we finally turn from some of the technical
discussions, you know, the halakhic discussions about the parameters of ריבית ribbit
from תורה ריבית Torah ribbit to דרבנן ריבית, D'rabbanan ribbit, אבק ריבית,
avak ribbit, to actually looking at the prohibitions associated with it. So
if you take a look in some sort of more broad, practical
issues, so if you take a look at the גמרא Gemara at
the bottom of עין עמוד א, Ayin Amud Aleph, we start with
quoting the פסוק. pasuk.
מרבה, Marbe, it is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, about 12 lines
from the bottom, line starts with the word מן הבכורה, Min habechora,
right, says משלי Mishlei in the left hand margin. Okay, מרבה הונו
בנשך ובתרבית, Marbe hono beneshech uvetarbit, the person who increases their wealth
through נשך neshech and תרבית, tarbit, through ריבית, ribbit, through charging interest,
לחונן דלים יקבצנו lechonin dallim yikabtzenu will gather it for the person
that will do kindness to the poor, meaning, so for a person,
let me get a sentence out. Okay, so anyway, will, right, maybe
it's God, okay fine, all right fine. So anyway, so you're trying
to become wealthy in the end of the day, your money is
ultimately going to go to the poor. You know, God will see
that it'll go to the poor. Right, Michael's correct, לחונן דלים chonin
dallim could mean God will ultimately gather but it could mean whatever,
the money will pass down to somebody who's going to give it
back to the poor. מאי לחונן דלים, Mai lechonin dallim, who is
this לחונן דלים, chonin dallim, what's meant by the פסוק? pasuk? אמר
רב Amar Rav כגון שבור מלכא, k'gon Shvor Malka, like שבור מלכא
Shvor Malka who was the Persian ruler, which is interesting, רש"י Rashi
says that the Persian ruler would basically take the wealth of, you
know, tax the Jews and give the money, distribute the money to
the poor of the non-Jews, which is all right fine, whatever, I
mean you know that happens in every government, people are taxed and
the money is redistributed, but presumably the גמרא's Gemara reading this that
that actually is what's is particularly the people who charge interest are
suffer this fate. So, so the point is, you know, the money
doesn't even stay within the Jewish people. You're charging interest and ultimately
the money is now going to be taxed and distributed to the
non-Jews. Okay that's at least the way רש"י Rashi understands it. Is
there a problem with this? You just trying to figure out where
we are? Okay fine, all right anyway. Okay so אמר רב נחמן,
Amar Rav Nachman, אמר לי הונא, Amar li Huna, so רב הונא
Rav Huna said to me, לא נצרכא אלא דאפילו ריבית דעובדי כוכבים.
lo nitzrecha ela d'afilo ribbit d'ovdei kochavim. Not only that, not only
is the money now going to be redistributed to the poor non-Jews,
but this would even be true about ריבית ribbit that was charged
to non-Jews, which seems to be allowed in the תורה, Torah, not
only allowed maybe even maybe even like encouraged, but minimally allowed in
the תורה, Torah, לנכרי תשיך, lanachri tashich, and here the גמרא Gemara
is saying no, it's you should be staying away from the whole
thing even charging non-Jews and if you do ultimately you're going to
lose that money and it's going to be even, you know, redistributed.
That's why I posted that link right? So right, so anyway, כגון
שבור מלכא k'gon Shvor Malka is distributed. Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara
says exactly, so the גמרא Gemara says איתיבי רבא לרב נחמן, Eitibi
Rava l'Rav Nachman, so רבא Rava asked רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, how
can you say that this is true that there's a problem about
charging interest to non-Jews, לנכרי תשיך, lanachri tashich, it says you shall
lend to the non-Jew with interest. Now, מאי לאו תשיך, mai lav
tashich, now again we get back to a point in the beginning
of the גמרא Gemara that the גמרא Gemara assumes that the word
תשיך tashich actually means to borrow with interest. And the גמרא Gemara
really reads this as from the foreigner you will borrow, you may
borrow with interest. And the גמרא Gemara says and doesn't it also
include the idea that you can lend the foreigner with interest? מאי
תשיך, לאו תשיך mai tashich, lav tashich doesn't it mean you could
lend the foreigner with interest? So the גמרא Gemara says לאו, תשיך,
lav, tashich, no, you have to borrow, you borrow from them with
interest but you're not allowed to lend. So the גמרא Gemara says
all right and how does that make sense? לא סגי דלאו הכי,
lo sagi d'lav hachi, so
so what, so you're only allowed, so so you're supposed to borrow
with interest from the non-Jew? Like what does that mean? Like why
is the תורה Torah encouraging that or allow you know or sort
of pointing that out? It's one thing to say you can lend
them with interest, why is it saying you borrow from them with
interest? So the גמרא Gemara says no, לאפוקי אחיך דלא, l'afukei achicha
d'lo, no it's right, the תורה Torah doesn't have to tell you
you can borrow from the non-Jew with interest but it's to tell
you to imply only from the non-Jew can you borrow from interest
and you can't borrow from the Jew with interest. So the גמרא
Gemara says ואחיך בהדיא כתיב ביה, v'achicha behedya ketiv beh, what do
you mean? It explicitly says not to borrow from your fellow Jew
with interest. ולאחיך לא תשיך, v'lachicha lo sashich, the next words, don't,
again, you have to take for granted that the גמרא Gemara here
is reading the word תשיך tashich meaning to borrow, not to lend,
which I don't think is פשט pshat at all, but anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara says the next words say don't borrow from a
Jew with interest. So why do you have to imply it by
saying borrow from a non-Jew with interest? So the גמרא Gemara says
לעבור בלאו עשה ולא תעשה. la'avor b'lav aseh v'lo ta'aseh. All right
to in order to make it doubly prohibited. Do not borrow from
your fellow Jew with interest and only borrow if you're going to
borrow from interest, only be from a non-Jew. So when you borrow
from a Jew you've transgressed even that positive מצוה mitzvah that you're
supposed to only borrow from a non-Jew. Anyway what we've done is
we've basically limited the פסוקים psukim to talk about borrowing so and
to get out of the fact that the פסוקים psukim should speak
seem to be explicitly condoning lending to a non-Jew with interest. Now
the question is as we know just from the whole history of
the middle ages, right, since when is it אסור assur to lend
a non-Jew with interest? Why is the גמרא Gemara sort of... choosing
to discourage that activity and to even resist reading the פסוקים pesukim
to allow it? So we're going to see in a minute. Let's
continue the גמרא Gemara a little bit. איתיבי. Eitivi.
לווים מהן ומלווין אותן ברבית. Lovin mehen umalvin otan beribbit.
You can borrow from them and lend to them, them obviously being
non-Jews, with רבית. ribbit. So it's a מפורש meforash teaching that you're
allowed to lend to non-Jews with רבית. ribbit. So why were you
discouraging it before, that statement that God will take away your wealth
if you lend to non-Jews with interest? So the גמרא Gemara says,
וכן בגר תושב. vechen beger toshav. Not only is it allowed to
non-Jews, it's even allowed to a גר תושב, ger toshav, I mean
to, not just standard non-Jews, even to a גר תושב, ger toshav,
who's a non-Jew who's accepted the שבע מצוות בני נח sheva mitzvot
benei Noach and so on. So it's explicit. So אמר רב חייא
בריה דרב הונא לא נצרכה אלא בכדי חייו. Amar Rav Chiya berei
deRav Huna lo nitzrecha ella bichdei chayav. Okay, fine, it is explicit.
It is מותר mutar to lend to a non-Jew with interest. But
only, not to go ahead and make like a business and a
big profit out of it and get wealthy. Only minimally what you
need to do to support yourself. Okay, you need to make a
basic פרנסה parnassah and put food on the table, you can lend
to non-Jews with interest. But you should not do it to become
wealthy. Now clearly if they say, we're not claiming that it's not
allowed from the תורה. Torah. If it's not allowed from the תורה,
Torah, you would not make these distinctions. Clearly there's some rabbinic concern
here that is yes, obviously in the context to go back to
the earlier פסוקים. pesukim. Fine, it's מותר mutar to lend non-Jews with
interest. But the רבנים Rabbanim didn't like it and they only allowed
it up to basically making a basic פרנסה. parnassah. Now what's the
concern? What's the concern? What is the rabbinic concern? So if you
look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says, בכדי חייו התירו לו. bichdei
chayav hittiru lo. That amount the רבנים Rabbanim allowed, ויותר מכאן אסור
מדרבנן. veyoter mikan asur miderabbanan.
Again, now רש״י Rashi makes it clear, it's fine, forget the idea
that there's a תורה Torah problem, it's rabbinic. דילמא אתי למיסרך. dilma
ati lemisrach.
Maybe you'll come to be dragged after, which presumably means that once
you make a big business, well, that's one possibility, one possibility is
you'll learn from non-Jews, which is what we'll get to in a
minute. But the other possibility is you'll be dragged after this behavior.
Once you're making a big profit lending with interest, why close out
a whole market? You've got all the Jews to lend with interest
to.
So because the thing is אסור asur when done with Jews, you
don't want, you want to sort of always relate to it with
a certain amount of hesitation. Right?
You don't want to give too much of a license to oh,
yeah, go ahead, make a lot of money lending with interest. That
sends a signal, so oh but why I might as well lend
with Jews with interest? So you always want to keep a sense
of limits and restrictions. That's one answer. But the other now גמרא
Gemara continues that has more to do with interaction with non-Jews. רבינא
אמר הכא בתלמידי חכמים עסקינן. Ravina amar hacha betalmidie chachamim askinan. No,
when is it permissible to lend non-Jews with interest? Forget the idea
of how much you're lending. That's when you're dealing with ישיבה yeshiva
students, right, תורה Torah scholars. טעם מאי גזרו רבנן שמא ילמד ממעשיו.
Taama mai gazaru Rabbanan shema yilmad mimaasav. So this gives a different
reason or maybe it's another way of reading the רש״י Rashi of
דילמא אתי למיסרך. dilma ati lemisrach. Okay, the reason is that if
you have too much interaction, like you get non-Jews walking in and
out of your door every single day coming to borrow money, right?
So it's regular interactions. And not only that, like you could say,
well does that mean that I can't go into business because I
have non-Jewish customers? No, but here the idea is your customer base
is limited to non-Jews. Right? You cannot engage Jews with this business.
So you have to be soliciting non-Jewish business and getting involved in
the non-Jewish community. Well that's going to draw you after the non-Jew,
okay? That's going to like lead to pulling you away from Jewish
observance
or at least, you know, a Jewish ethics or whatever. שמא ילמד
ממעשיו, shema yilmad mimaasav, וכיון דתלמיד חכם הוא לא ילמד ממעשיו. vekeivan
detalmid chacham hu lo yilmad mimaasav. And since he's a תלמיד חכם,
talmid chacham, though he's careful enough not to learn from that. So
here we get the idea that תורה, Torah, yes, okay, but no,
that's where I tried to emphasize that it's not just any interaction
with non-Jews, it's something that is completely limited and that the whole
way you make money is by focusing, is by ignoring, not dealing
with Jews and totally focusing your efforts with the non-Jews. But what
does that mean? It means that I can't go ahead and go
to a market, I got the slave market in China where I
can go ahead and make a lot of money, I'm not allowed
to do it because I'm only going to be dealing with
non-Jews? So I assume that it's also a little bit of the
other element, that this is something that is אסור asur in other
contexts, so we remain a little bit hesitant. But what you have
here in the גמרא Gemara is that while it's obviously permitted in
the תורה Torah to lend to non-Jews with interest, it is rabbinically
we put restrictions on it, whether it's a concern about, about just
generally not giving yourself too much license because it's, because it'll lead
to lending with Jews, you want to always treat it as a
דבר אסור, davar asur, something like that, or because it focuses your
interactions with non-Jews. So the question is, well what do you do
about the entire ways in which Jews in Christian Europe earned money
in the Middle Ages? Right, by the way, I assume everybody knows
that the reason this was the primary enterprise of Jews in the
Middle Ages in Christian Europe is because, as opposed to Muslim lands,
is because the Christians would not let Jews own land and they
would restrict Jews from most other businesses. This was one of the
few businesses that was left open to Jews. And because the Christians
took upon themselves the prohibition of lending interest, whereas to fellow Christians.
So the only way Christians could borrow money was by borrowing it
from Jews. So it actually was quite interesting. This was one of
the איסורים issurim in the Torah that the Christians actually, you know,
in terms of like, you know, that even post-Jesus decided that it
was still binding on them as it applied to fellow Christians. So
anyway, so how did—but what did we do about these restrictions
not—to non-Christians? Their אחיך—I'm achicha totally serious. Their אחיך achicha was Christian.
Okay, so the—so anyway, and people needed to borrow money. So, put
that—anyway, so of course as we know, that led to terrible antisemitism
and Jews as money lenders and the whole thing. Anyway, take a
look here תוספות, Tosafot, תשיך. tashich. תוספות Tosafot says the following.
He says, bottom of ע"ב Ayin Amud Bet before...
okay, he says like this. ומה
שנהגו עכשיו, u-mah she-nahagu achshav, the bottom of ע"ב, Ayin Amud Bet,
the תשיך, tashich, it's about fifth line into that תוספות, Tosafot, line
starts with the word שנהגו. she-nahagu. Okay. ומה שנהגו עתה להלוות לנכרים,
u-mah she-nahagu ata le-halvot le-nochrim,
now we have a practice of lending to non-Jews. אמר רבינו תם
Amar Rabbeinu Tam משום דסוברים הלכה כהאי מיקל. mishum de-savrin halacha ke-hai
meikel.
It's a rabbinic issue, this restriction to non-Jews, and we're lenient by
rabbinic issues. Now, so who are we relying on? דקיימא לן כאידך
לישנא דמסקי התם דרב הונא אברייתא דרב יוסף ואסר מעולם רב נחמן
ורב הונא ריבית דנכרי. de-kaima lan ke-idach lishana de-maski hatam de-Rav Huna
a-baraita de-Rav Yosef ve-asar me-olam Rav Nachman ve-Rav Huna ribit de-nochri.
So we're going to see in a minute that this statement that
said, you know, remember the statement said, אפילו, afilu, you know, אפילו,
afilu,
what was the statement? אמר רב נחמן אמר לי הונא לא נצרכה
אלא אפילו ריבית של עובד כוכבים, Amar Rav Nachman amar li Huna
lo nitzrecha ela afilu ribit shel oved kochavim, right? So that was
the statement. Even ריבית ribit of a non-Jew. So we said that
means you're not supposed to lend a non-Jew with interest. But we're
going to see in a minute that the גמרא Gemara applies that
line to a completely different context. So תוספות's Tosafot's first answer is
we're going to go like this second לשון lashon in the גמרא,
Gemara, which we're about to read, that this statement was never said.
It was never said in the context that you cannot lend a
non-Jew with interest. So number one, we don't פסק pasken like this
at all. Okay. Number two, ואפילו ללישנא קמא, ve-afilu le-lishana kama, even
according to what we just read, that it is said that a
non-Jew's—you should limit your interactions of lending with interest, יש להתיר, yesh
le-hatir, you can still allow it. לפי שיש עלינו מס המלך והשרים.
le-fi she-yesh aleinu mas ha-melech ve-ha-sarim. We have heavy taxes on us
now from the king and from the—the שרים sarim are the, whatever,
you know, the—the—the nobles,
right? It was feudal—it was feudal lands. והכל הוי כדי חיינו. ve-ha-kol
havei kedei chayeinu. Any money that we can earn is כדי חיינו.
kedei chayeinu. Anything is earning a basic פרנסה. parnassa. So even I
guess it means if some Jews got very wealthy, maybe they assumed
the whole trickle-down effect—I'm serious—that as a general rule, the Jewish community
had very limited options of earning money, you have to allow, you
know, any money to come into the community and therefore it's all
considered to be basic sustenance. Why? Just means someone—meaning because if I
make a lot of money, then I'm going to do business within
the Jewish community and right, exactly. That's what I'm—how I'm reading תוספות.
Tosafot. Okay. Because you know, so number one is it's all considered
basic sustenance. ועוד. Ve-od. One is we פסק pasken like somebody else.
One is we פסק—we pasken don't פסק pasken this גמרא, Gemara, we
פסק pasken the next לשון, lashon, which we're about to read. Number
two is it's all basic sustenance. ועוד שאנו שרויין בין האומות ואי
אפשר לנו להשתכר בשום
דבר. Ve-od she-anu sheruyin bein ha-umot ve-ee efshar lanu le-histaker be-shum davar.
We—we're among the non-Jews, we have no opportunity to earn money with
anything else. אם לא נישא וניתן עמהם, im lo nisa ve-nitan imahem,
unless we do this, we lend with interest. הלכך אין לאסור ריבית.
hilkach ein le-asor ribit. Now, so how's that different than the כדי
חיינו kedei chayeinu answer? So here's the answer: לא לאסור ריבית שמא
ילמוד ממעשיו יותר משאר משא ומתן. lo le-asor ribit shema yilmod mi-ma'asav
yoter mi-sha'ar masa u-matan.
It's the point I said before, it's like going ahead and selling—you
have a market in China. תוספות Tosafot says you're not making a
choice. Like, it's one thing if you said you could choose to
do a nice business within the Jewish community and you're running to
make money to—to deal with the non-Jew. תוספות Tosafot says we don't
have any other options. So we don't have any other options when
they—this was to say you shouldn't lend to non-Jews was when there
were other reasonable options, this was not the ideal choice. But if
there are no other reasonable options and this is where you can
make your פרנסה parnassa and this is the only opportunity, then this
is permissible. And we told some תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim then another
thing also gets off the ground, right? There's—the first answer was כדי
חיינו kedei chayeinu we let everyone. Yeah, תוספות Tosafot is not limiting
this to תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. Right. No, I know. But if
you look at the תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, and that's the—the only
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and even that's כדי חיינו kedei chayeinu maybe?
What? It sounds like the רמב"ם, Rambam, the one that says it's
רק תלמידי חכמים, rak talmidei chachamim, would the תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
have a license to do it no matter what, or is it
כדי חיינו? kedei chayeinu? It sounds like—no, sounds like... It's out of
the רמ"א, Rema, yeah, תוספות's Tosafot's לשון... lashon... He says everyone's כדי
חיינו, kedei chayeinu, תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim even
better. But he פסק paskens both היתרים. heterim. Right. Right, exactly, both
היתרים heterim could be true. Everybody's כדי חיינו kedei chayeinu and תלמידי
חכמים, talmidei chachamim, no limits. Anyway, but תוספות Tosafot says that obviously
that, you know, has to do away with—with getting rid of these
restrictions, so either he's going to say we don't פסק pasken it
at all, or both היתרים heterim apply to us. Everything is considered
to be a basic sustenance, and
the problem of ילמוד ממעשיו yilmod mi-ma'asav is only when it's an
equivalent choice. When it's not an equivalent choice, then of course it's
allowed. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues. So very—obviously a very, very
relevant... Now the גמרא Gemara says, and it's also always nice to
see a little, like, you know, history brought in from תוספות's Tosafot's
discussion. Okay. איכא דמתני לה, Ika de-matni lah, now here's the other
לשון lashon that תוספות Tosafot says doesn't even read this to have
applied to restrict lending to non-Jews. איכא דמתני להא דרב הונא אהא
דתני רב יוסף. Ika de-matni le-ha de-Rav Huna a-ha de-tani Rav Yosef.
Some teach this of Rav Huna on this which Rav Yosef taught.
taught that statement of רב הונא Rav Huna about ריבית ribbis of
non-Jews, not to restrict, but on the following teaching of רב יוסף.
Rav Yosef. What does רב יוסף Rav Yosef teach? Very, very famous,
this is hugely important in terms of laws of צדקה tzedakah and
so on, the next line we're about to read. It's interesting that
it gets brought in in the ריבית ribbis context. אם כסף תלוה
את עמי את העני עמך. Im kesef talveh es ami es he'ani
imach. If you lend money to my nation to the poor among
you. So this now tells you, says רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, a
hierarchy of how you're supposed to lend money. And by the way,
all these פסוקים psukim in the תורה Torah about lending money are
often immediately translated by חז״ל, Chazal, when it talks about lending money
to Jews as also obligations of צדקה, tzedakah, of giving money to
Jews. We should point out why that is for a moment. According
to the
תורה, Torah, if I will challenge anybody to find anywhere in the
תורה Torah where it says you have a מצוה mitzvah to give
money to the poor. The only time in the תורה Torah you
give something to the poor is in the context of לקט שכחה
ופאה leket shikcha u'peah and so on, okay, which has a certain
amount of dignity, the poor come and they actually work for it
and they gather and so on. פתוח תפתח, Pasoach tiftach, if you
read the פסוקים psukim is about lending money, it is not about
giving money. So all the פסוקים psukim in the תורה Torah about
money are about lending money. Now the reason is, you know, when
you give somebody a straight out gift, charity, alms, or whatever, it
can obviously, you know, be a, compromise their sense of dignity, you
know, they're, you know, as they're, they're dependent on you and the
whole thing. When you lend money, it retains that sense of dignity,
you're lending and I'm gonna pay back and I'm an equal member
of society, I've not cast myself at the mercy of others and
so on. Okay, the only problem is, is that if you lend
money, sometimes I won't be able to pay back and I'll also
have to pay interest, so etc. So the תורה Torah addresses those
problems. It says after seven years, if you can't pay back, the
loan is wiped clean. You don't have to pay interest. So actually
it's the best of both worlds. You borrow the money in a,
you get the money in a way of borrowing which preserves your
dignity as opposed to just receiving it as alms, and at the
other hand, you don't have the bad stuff about the borrowing, you
try to pay back which is also good because it helps you
know, keep, it means keep recycling the same money and so on,
and it makes me more industrious if I have to pay back.
But if you can't, then it gets wiped clean and you also
will be protected from interest. So that's why in the תורה, Torah,
the צדקה tzedakah of money is lending money. But חז״ל Chazal immediately
interpret all these פסוקים psukim also to be referring or primarily sometimes
to be referring to giving money. Anyway, so what we're about to
read is a priority of lending money, but you might have been
familiar with this teaching around issues of priorities of צדקה, tzedakah, because
that's how it's usually translated as. All right, אם כסף תלוה את
עמי את העני עמך, Im kesef talveh es ami es he'ani imach,
עמי ונכרי עמי קודם. Ami v'nochri ami kodem. My nation and the
foreigner, אם כסף תלוה את עמי, Im kesef talveh es ami, so
the first person you have an obligation to lend money to is
my nation, עמי קודם. ami kodem. Okay, עמי קודם. ami kodem. עני
ועשיר, Ani v'ashir, if you have to choose between giving it to
a poor person or a wealthy person, עני קודם. ani kodem. אם
כסף תלוה את עמי, Im kesef talveh es ami, so first you
lend to my nation. Even within my nation, there's a priority, את
העני. es he'ani. You first have to lend to poor before you
lend to wealthy, עני קודם. ani kodem. Now within lending to poor
people, את העני עמך, es he'ani imach, the poor person that is
closer to you is the person you have the prior obligation to.
ענייך ועניי עירך, Aniyecha v'aniyei ircha, your poor, meaning the poor of
your family, and the poor of your town, ענייך קודמים. aniyecha kodmim.
Then it's your poor, because it's עמך, imach, those that are closer
to you you have a greater obligation. עניי עירך ועניי עיר אחרת,
Aniyei ircha v'aniyei ir acheres, those of your town or another town,
עניי עירך קודמים, aniyei ircha kodmim, your town comes first. So this
is a big teaching in the context of priorities of צדקה. tzedakah.
The important thing to note though is that well there are two
basic, that there first of all is that there are two different
criteria
going on here. One is degree of closeness. Those that are closer
to you you have a greater obligation. Closeness could be defined as
geographically closer, my city and another city, they could be defined as
relationship closeness, my relatives, my family, people that are not my relatives,
and also about a sense of, you know, closeness in terms of
coreligionists, or you want that as a form of family, Jews versus
non-Jews. Okay, but one measure is degree of closeness, so closeness defined
in different ways. The other measure is degree of need, poor versus
rich. Raises very interesting questions of which one of those is more
important, right? Somebody in another town, they need money for food and
for clothing, but my relative needs money to send their kids to
a better school, you know, so what's the priority, right? So it's
a big discussion in the פוסקים, poskim, which of those two, which
of those two sort of criteria, you know, what's the right mix
or balance of those two criteria? It's not clear in the גמרא,
Gemara, different פוסקים poskim have different opinions. Okay, so if the poor
person is not Jewish, you still give to... So the other issue,
so the other issue is when the גמרא Gemara says my nation
and the foreigner, my nation comes first, does that mean that I
do have an obligation to a foreigner, it's just lower on the
list of priorities? It sounds that way actually. Although it is rare
to find a פוסק posek that says that. המאירי, ha'Meiri, who often
is very inclusive... of non-Jews, you know, tries to sort of read
more of a broader sense of obligation towards non-Jews, the מאירי Meiri
actually says that explicitly, that there is an element of obligation, of
real, you know, towards non-Jews to lending with צדקה. tzedakah. I mean,
it's a broader question, what's our general sense of obligation to non-Jews,
you know, you know, obviously quote broad פסוקים: psukim: והלכת בדרכיו, vehalachta
bidrachav, דרכי שלום, darchei shalom, etcetera. But is there a technical צדקה
tzedakah obligation to non-Jews? So this might seem that the answer is
yes, except that it's lower on the priority list. And the מאירי
Meiri sort of says that, although he waffles a little. He says,
at least as an ethical obligation to them, or there's a little
obligation to them. Mostly people read that non-Jews here are being completely
excluded from the obligation, and the rest is setting priorities. But the
simple language of this ברייתא braita is that non-Jews are, you
are obligated, it's just different in terms of the degree of priority.
Yes. So it's a little strange the way I see it as
a הלכה halakha point, and I always wondered about this because if
it's purely in terms of priorities, then the first priority is never
exhausted, right? There's always poor people, right, in basic necessity before you
move on to somebody else far away. Right. So the ערוך השולחן
Aruch Hashulchan basically raises that. He says, so you're supposed to give
all your money to those that are in your immediate family even
if there's people that are desperately in need? So that's why there
are two, you know, there's, you know, there's like two, there's two
different sets of criteria. But you are correct that let's basically, you
know, you could sort of say, okay, but even within the let's
say proximity criteria, right? So let's say so, so if there's equal
level of needs within, you know, whatever, my family and or this
town and the neighboring town, I'm not supposed to give any money
to the neighboring town because, you know, because so, yeah, so that's
why these are seen more as like guidelines, rather than like these
aren't like the laws of a כשר kosher אתרוג, etrog, you know?
These are more general guidelines. Specifically the הלכה halakha process would end
up by saying, you know, X percentage to the rest. Right. So
I think it's very interesting in general that in areas of what
I would call like ethical areas, or בין אדם לחבירו, bein adam
lachaveiro, the, the degree of specificity and of quantification is much less
than in quite cases of like like what what you know whether
I have to repeat יעלה ויבוא yaale veyavo and you know it's
December 5th or what on what my אתרוג etrog has to look
like. And I there's two reasons. One is because the reality of
the human condition is, you know, can't be quantified. Like you know,
the degrees of context and circumstances can never be reduced to a
certain set of criteria. But the other reason is I think because
we want these מצוות mitzvot to not just be following rules, we
want them to be exercising your, you know, your ethical judgment. We
want them to be continued to be ethical acts. And if all
you're doing is looking up in the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, oh,
this is how I have to distribute my money today because the
שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch says this is how you distribute it, then
it just becomes rule following and it doesn't become an ethical act.
So but it is true that adaptation or? I don't know. That's
me philosophizing, but I do note that as a, it's not a,
it's not an exception. Generally you find in the ethical realm that
things are much less specified, you know, much more allow certain context
and a degree of judgment that you don't find in other areas.
Yes. So make sure I'm getting this. So let's say the choice
is between like the poor non-Jew, let's say, you know this guy
is not Jewish, homeless on the street, or like, you know, sending
someone else to ישיבה yeshiva day school? Right. Would that win based
on what we're saying here? Because there's עניי, aniyei, you know, your
co-religionists versus the other. I mean. Yes. That's basically you're saying that.
Well, no, I mean we don't know. It's too, you have different
sets of criteria. You don't know which one is more important. So
they, it remains unclear. It could simply be what Ashley said. They,
what? That, oh in terms of the non-Jew case? No, non-Jew in
general, that's what I said. In general, even the מאירי Meiri who
generally is more inclusive of non-Jews says there's a somewhat obligation to
non-Jews. So the non-Jews are not read as just a priority. It's
read as much more of a more categorical different type of obligation.
Okay. Moving on. So the one other thing I should say about
the idea that your obligation is greater to those closer to you,
I should point out that that's in my mind one of the
most important Jewish ethical principles, which is, which is basically חייך וחיי
אחיך חייך קודמים, chayecha vechayei achicha chayecha kodmim, right? Which is not
just true about your life, but it's also true about your, you
know, your just your financial well-being, which doesn't mean your needs come
before your desires come before other people, it doesn't mean you enrich
yourself at other people's expense, you know, rather than taking care of
other people, but it does mean that you do have a primary
responsibility to protect, you know, to to yourself. So that's just an
extension of the idea that your obligation is greater to those closer
to you. Who's closer to you than yourself? Okay. So anyway the
גמרא Gemara now continues. So, so what does this have to do
with anything we're discussing? So אמר מר, amar mar, עמי ונכרי עמי
קודם. ami venochri ami kodem. My nation and the foreigner, my nation
comes first. פשיטא. peshita. Obviously, right?
So it's just a פשיטא peshita that for many פוסקים poskim besides
a general inclination, leads them to they treat this as not just
a priority issue but as a complete exclusion. Anyway, אמר רב נחמן
אמר רב הונא, amar Rav Nachman amar Rav Huna, לא נצרכה דאפילו
לנכרי בריבית ולישראל בחינם. lo nitzrecha deafilu lenochri beribbit uleyisrael bechinam. Ah,
here's the statement. The statement of a of a non-Jew with ריבית
ribbit is not You're not allowed to lend a non-Jew with ריבית.
ribis. We never said such a thing. The statement is that if
you have a choice between lending to a non-Jew with interest and
you could actually make a פרנסה parnassah off of it and make
some money or lending to a Jew and for free and you're
obviously not going to make money that way, okay, you nevertheless have
to lend your money to the Jews and not to the non-Jew.
Okay, so it's not that the priority aspect is obvious but here
it's telling you that you even have to forgo a certain amount
of financial gain. Now, what does that mean? I mean, if I'm
in the business of lending money with interest to non-Jews, like do
I have to now take away all of my funds that I
use for that business in order to lend to a Jew? Presumably
not. Right. Presumably not. Presumably not talking about somebody who's in the
business of doing that, we're talking about I'm just סתם stam a
guy and a non-Jew comes and says, "Lend me a thousand dollars,
I'll even pay you interest," and the Jew says, "I need the
thousand dollars," so you have to give it to the Jew. Okay.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. And this
is what תוספות Tosafos is like, well he says one way to
understand is that we read it this way and we never restricted
lending to a non-Jew with interest at all. Okay. Yeah, I say,
Rabbi, yes, like underline all like I get all of that, but
in other words, it is so obvious that it would create animosity.
Right. The whole thing creates animosity. Right. Well, yeah, so I mean,
obviously, well first of all the flip side of this is the
whole מפני דרכי שלום, mipnei darchei shalom, which is exactly that which
recognizes that as, you know, Seth was saying, the insularity or whatever
can create obviously create enormous amount of animosity, that's איבה eivah and
דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. But even that, that's just a practical reaction,
like, you know, you don't want to do things that get people
angry. Then there's other later discussions to see this as even an
ethical obligation like the המאירי haMeiri I mentioned, רמב״ם Rambam reads דרכי
שלום darchei shalom as not just self-interest and ways of getting them
to act nicely but רמב״ם Rambam says דרכי שלום darchei shalom is
דרך התורה derech haTorah because תורה Torah is כל נתיבותיה שלום kol
nesivoseha shalom and it's basically, you know, an ethics that you extend
to all people. So there are different voices in the גמרא, Gemara,
okay. דרך התורה. Derech haTorah. Exactly. All right, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. תניא Tanya אמר רבי יוסי amar Rabbi Yosi
בוא וראה סמיות עיניהם של מלוי בריבית. bo u'rei sumyos eineihem shel
malvei b'ribis.
Go and see the blindness of people who lend with ריבית, ribis,
how they could be so blind to their own to, you know,
whatever their own reputation. אדם קורא לחבירו רשע, Adam korei l'chaveiro rasha,
if somebody were to call if somebody would call somebody else a
רשע, rasha, יורד עמו לחייו, yored imo l'chayav, the person who would
be so offended that he would like make the other guy's life
a living hell. Okay. So nobody wants to be called a רשע.
rasha. Nevertheless, you're going to lend with ריבית. ribis. What are you
doing? You're about to do this big עבירה aveira that you're going
to lend with ריבית. ribis. הם מביאים עדים ולבלר וקולמוס. Heim mevi'im
eidim v'lavlar v'kulmos. You make a big production out of this big
עבירה aveira you're about to do. You bring witnesses and a scribe
and the and the quill, ודיו v'dyo and the ink, וכותבים וחותמים
v'kosvim v'chosmim and you write and you sign and here's what you're
signing in your שטר. shtar. You don't realize this, but this is
what you're signing to: פלוני זה כפר באלהי ישראל. Ploni zeh kafar
b'Elohei Yisrael. This person who's lending with ריבית, ribis, I am rejecting
the God of Israel. So you're basically announcing to everybody how you're
such a רשע rasha that you're lending with ריבית. ribis. You're not
hiding it. You know, most people, you do a חטא, cheit, do
it in private at least. Okay, and it just shows how blind
you are to the statement that you're making about yourself. All right,
this somehow reminds me of the story I forget who it was
about but I think it was I don't know I remember the
נודע ביהודה Noda B'Yehuda it could have been somebody else. Anyway, so
somebody in the town like lent money with interest and made like,
you know, became very wealthy at the expense of his fellow Jews
and when he died the townspeople did not want the חברה קדישא
chevra kadisha charged wanted to charge the heirs an exorbitant amount for
the plot, you know figure the town will at least get back
some of the money that they've lost to this guy over the
years. So the family sue sued and brought them to to secular
court. Like they said, "This isn't fair, there's a standard price for
the plot, we shouldn't have to pay." So they brought them to
secular court, so whoever it is, I'm going to say the נודע
ביהודה Noda B'Yehuda came to testify and he said, "Look," he said,
"The standard price is for everybody else because really we Jews we
believe in תחיית המתים. techiyas hameisim. So when you're buying a funeral
plot you're not really buying it, you're just it's a rental. So
that's the price for the rental." He says, "But the גמרא Gemara
says מלוה בריבית אין להם חלק לעולם הבא. malveh b'ribis ein lahem
cheilek l'olam haba. So for him it's a permanent sale, so it's
a fair price."
All right, anyway, so all right. But what is again fascinating is
that the גמרא Gemara acknowledges here as it does in a few
cases that there's a segment of the population that is just blatantly,
you know, flagrantly, you know, violating the תורה Torah law. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. תניא Tanya ותנא ברייתא v'tana braisa
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer כל מי
שיש לו מעות ומלוה אותם שלא בריבית. kol mi sheyesh lo ma'os
u'malveh osam shelo b'ribis.
If you have money and you lend them without ריבית, ribis, עליו
הכתוב אומר alav hakasuv omer כספו לא נתן בנשך. kaspo lo nasan
b'neshech. You never gave your money with interest, ושוחד על נקי לא
לקח v'shochad al naki lo lakach and you never took a bribe
to judge guilty, you know, to judge an innocent person guilty. עושה
אלה לא ימוט לעולם. Oseh eileh lo yimmot l'olam. If somebody who
acts this way will never stumble. הא למדת, Ha lamadta, it teaches
you שכל המלוה בריבית shekol hamalveh b'ribis that if you do lend
with נכסיו מתמוטטין, Nechasav mismotetin, your property will fail, will falter. Eventually
all your wealth
will be lost. That's the best way to try to scare people
to not sin because if the reason they're doing it is because
they think they're going to get rich, so if they say, no,
no, no, you're not going to get rich, all the money is
going to get lost. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, והא חזינן
דלא מוזפי בריבית וקא מתמוטטין. Veha chazinan delo mozfi beribis veka mismotetin.
It's interesting. The גמרא Gemara could challenge this. I would have expected
the גמרא Gemara to challenge it to say we see people lending
with interest and they don't lose their money. Now maybe it did
want to say that, but you don't want to admit that because
if you admit that in print, that's a little dangerous to admit
that phenomenon. So the גמרא Gemara asks the other phenomenon. We see
people don't lend with ריבית ribis and still they lose their money
in the stock market or whatever. A lot of innocent people lose
their money. So it's not true that if you don't lend with
ריבית ribis your money is protected. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar,
הללו מתמוטטין ועולין והללו מתמוטטין ואינן עולין. Halalu mismotetin veolin vehalalu mismotetin
veeinan olin.
No, no. If you don't lend with ריבית, ribis, sometimes your fortunes
go down, but then they go up again. So later the stock
market will go up. But if you lend with ריבית, ribis, the
fortunes go down and they never come up again. All right, I
don't know if that's actually true, but
exactly. Anyway, it's an important statement to make. Okay. למה תביט בוגדים,
Lama sabit bogdim, now continuing this context, why God do you look
at the spoilers, תחריש בבלע רשע צדיק ממנו, Tacharish bevala rasha tzaddik
mimennu,
you're silent when the wicked person swallows up the one who is
more righteous than he. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, צדיק ממנו
בולע צדיק גמור אינו בולע. Tzaddik mimennu bolea tzaddik gamur eino bolea.
The wicked can swallow up somebody who's more righteous than he on
a relative scale, but he will not be able to destroy somebody
who's totally righteous, objectively righteous. So this seems the way רש״י Rashi
reads this as reinforcing the point we said before. Somebody who's really
a צדיק tzaddik will never totally lose their wealth. It might go
down, but it'll come up again. Okay. So but again, now we're
limiting it to a צדיק גמור, tzaddik gamur, which also helps because
now there's a lot of phenomenon that don't fit with this model,
but now we're limiting it to a צדיק גמור. tzaddik gamur. Okay.
תניא, Tanya, it's taught in a ברייתא. braisa. רבי אומר, Rebbi omer,
גר צדק אמור לענין מכירה וגר תושב אמור לענין ריבית. Ger tzedek
amur leinyan mechira veger toshav amur leinyan ribis. When the תורה Torah
talks about a righteous convert, about a convert in the case about
sale, and when it talks about a גר תושב, ger toshav, a
resident alien in the case of ריבית, ribis, איני יודע מהו. Eini
yodea mahu. I don't know how to read that properly into the
פסוק. passuk. What does that mean? So now we're going to unpack
this statement. גר צדק אמור לענין מכירה דכתיב, Ger tzedek amur leinyan
mechira dechsiv, וכי ימוך אחיך עמך ונמכר לך. Vechi yamuch achicha imach
venimkar lach. Okay, when your brother gets poor and is sold to
you and he sells himself as a slave, don't work him, don't
take advantage, don't work him overly hard. So it says, so this
is now the context here is that this פרשה parsha appears right
after the whole פרשה parsha about שמיטה. shemita. And the מוסר mussar
that חז״ל Chazal give about this פרשה parsha is if you do
business with שמיטה, shemita, and again, because you're trying to get wealthy
in a way that you shouldn't, in the end you'll become poor
and you'll sell your field and you'll sell your house and then
your daughter and eventually you'll sell yourself. Okay, and then it keeps
on going in terms of how your fortunes are going to continue
to get worse and worse.
Okay, so ונמכר לך, venimkar lach, sold to you, a fellow Jew.
ולא לך, Velo lach, not only to a fellow Jew, אלא לגר,
Ela leger, even sells himself to a גר, ger, presumably a גר
תושב, ger toshav, a גר צדק, ger tzedek, excuse me, a convert,
שנאמר
לגר. Sheneamar leger. ולא לגר צדק, Velo leger tzedek, not only to
a convert, אלא לגר תושב, Ela leger toshav, out of the nation,
he'll sell himself to a resident alien, שנאמר לגר תושב, Sheneamar leger
toshav, to a resident alien. And then the פסוק passuk says, או
לעקר משפחת גר. O leiker mishpachat ger. So משפחת גר mishpachat ger
זה הנכרי. zeh hanachri.
So now it's not just a resident alien, it's a true foreigner.
So if that's true, משפחת גר mishpachat ger means a true foreigner.
כשהוא אומר לעקר, Keshehu omer leiker, או לעקר, O leiker, it's a
hard word to translate, but anyway, but what does this word לעקר
leiker mean if it doesn't just mean a foreigner you're sold to
as a slave? It means דנמכר לעבודה זרה עצמה, Denimkar laavodah zarah
atzmah, you're sold actually to the pagan temple. רש״י Rashi says it
doesn't mean you necessarily worship עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, but you're hired
as a slave in the pagan temple and you're the one who
chops the wood and who cleans the floors and so on. עוקר.
Oker. Oh yeah, right. Right. Probably עקר eiker to uproot. All right.
Good point. You're uprooted completely from Jewish context. Anyway, so the point
is I don't get this idea when it says amongst these stages
of who you're sold to, so that's the מוסר. mussar. But amongst
these stages of who you could be sold to, one of them
is that you could be sold to a convert. He says I
don't understand that. An עבד עברי eved Ivri is not sold to
a גר. ger. Let's take a look. So he says, אמר מר
ולא לך לגר שנאמר
לגר. Amar mar velo lach leger sheneamar leger. למימרא, Lemeimra, so this
suggests, דגר קני עבד עברי, Deger kani eved Ivri, that a convert
can acquire a Jewish slave. רמינהי, Reminei, but I don't understand that
because we teach,
אין הגר נקנה בעבד עברי, Ein hager nikneh beeved Ivri, ואין אשה
וגר קונים עבד עברי. Veein ishah veger konim eved Ivri. A גר
ger cannot be sold as an עבד עברי, eved Ivri, and a
woman and a גר ger cannot purchase an עבד עברי. eved Ivri.
And now it's going to explain why. גר לא נקנה בעבד עברי.
Ger lo nikneh beeved Ivri. A גר Ger cannot be purchased as
an עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. He can't be an עבד עברי Eved
Ivri
because an עבד עברי Eved Ivri goes free at, you know, at
the יובל Yovel and says ושבת אל משפחתו Ve-shavta el mishpachto and
he will return to his family. Okay, בעינן, Be'inan, so you need
to return that פסוק Pasuk to be relevant to him. והא ליכא,
Ve-ha leka, and in this case he doesn't have a family to
return to. So, because he doesn't get the restoration to this ancestral
family, you know, that happens in the יובל, Yovel, he can never
be sold off to begin with. Which there's something very beautiful about
that because, you know, the גר Ger is already the convert, already
he's, right, he doesn't have a family. He, the sense, you know,
this, it's hard to have the same sense of belonging. So imagine
the greater sense of alienation that comes is that now you're actually
sold as a slave, which clearly has a sense that you're not
one of us and so on. So that degree of alienation is
tolerable by a naturally born Jew who already fundamentally has a sense
of belonging and will return to that sense of belonging, but it's
not acceptable by a גר. Ger. So a גר Ger can't be
sold as an עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. ואין אשה וגר קונים עבד
עברי. Ve-ein isha ve-ger konim eved ivri.
Okay, let's, והא ליכא, Ve-ha leka, ואין אשה וגר קונים עבד עברי.
Ve-ein isha ve-ger konim eved ivri. Now a גר Ger and a
woman cannot purchase an עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. Why not? אשה לאו
אורח ארעא. Isha lav orach ar'ah. A woman, it's not דרך ארץ,
Derech Eretz, you know, what's a woman doing having a male slave?
Who knows what's happening when we're not, you know, behind closed doors.
Okay, which is raises interesting questions because a man can purchase a
female slave, except, you know, when he buys a female slave, she's
under בת מצוה Bat Mitzvah and the purpose there is for marriage,
so maybe we see that as less
concerns. גר נמי, Ger nami, how come a גר Ger cannot purchase
an עבד עברי? Eved Ivri? גמירי, Gmiri, because we have a tradition,
דמקני קני ודלא מקני לא קני. D'maknei kanei v'dela maknei lo kanei.
One who is, you know, one who can be purchased as an
עבד עברי Eved Ivri can purchase an עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. One
who cannot be purchased, since a גר Ger himself cannot be sold
as an עבד עברי, Eved Ivri, he cannot own an עבד עברי
Eved Ivri either. So now we've got a problem. A גר Ger
can't own an עבד עברי, Eved Ivri, but this ברייתא Braita says
that, you know, ונמכר, Ve-nimkar, that speaks about being sold, it says
לגיר Le-ger means a convert. So how could it be sold to
a convert if we just said a convert can't own an עבד
עברי? Eved Ivri? So אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, so here's
the answer says רב נחמן בר יצחק, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, אינו
קונה, Eino koneh, no, no, no. It doesn't mean that a גר
Ger can't own an עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. A גר Ger can
own an עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. He can't own it כדין ישראל
Ke-din Yisrael and have the status of a ישראל Yisrael who owns
an עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. אבל קונה כדין נכרי. Aval koneh ke-din
nochri. He can own an עבד עברי Eved Ivri with the status
of a נכרי Nochri that a נכרי Nochri would have for owning
an עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. What's the difference if you sell yourself
to a Jew, sell yourself to a נכרי? Nochri? דכתיב דתניא, De-chtiv
de-tanya, הנרצע והנמכר לנכרי, Ha-nirtza ve-ha-nimkar le-nochri,
somebody who has had, you know, the עבד Eved that has had
the hole poked in the ear, so is sold until the יובל,
Yovel, and somebody sold to a נכרי, Nochri, אינו עובד לא את
הבן ולא את הבת. Eino oved lo et ha-ben ve-lo et ha-bat.
If the owner dies, does not continue working for the children. Okay,
if you're only sold, the irony is if you're only sold for
seven years or six years or whatever, it's a six-year contract, so
that contract remains binding if the owner dies and you continue to
work for the estate. But if it is a selling לעולם, Le-olam,
you know, that the hole is pierced or you're sold to a
נכרי, Nochri, that's seen more as a fuller purchase or, you know,
or maybe the other ways of understanding it, but anyway, and then
it's, but it's only a special responsibility only to the purchaser himself.
Okay, it doesn't extend to the second generation. So therefore, if a,
so a נכרי Nochri can own an עבד עברי, Eved Ivri, but
with the limit that if he dies, he won't pass it down
to his children. So the same is true about a גר. Ger.
Yes, a גר Ger can own an עבד עברי, Eved Ivri, that's
the פסוק, Pasuk, you know, או לגר או לעקר משפחת גר O
le-ger o le-eker mishpachat ger or whatever. But even though he can
be owned, he won't be owned as a, in the capacity of
a Jew owning him. Yes, I forget הנרצע Ha-nirtza is in perpetuity
or with the יובל Yovel goes out? Well, yes, to both. The
תורה Torah says לעולם, Le-olam, but חז"ל Chazal understand the לעולם Le-olam
is limited by the יובל. Yovel. Okay, but anyway, so that's the
answer. Yes, he can be owned by a גר, Ger, it's just
that he will not pass down to the son. For some reason
I thought it sounds such a עקר משפחה, Eker mishpacha, it goes
to פסוקים. Pesukim. Yeah, so we're just reading the פסוק, Pasuk, או
לגר או לעקר משפחת גר. O le-ger o le-eker mishpachat ger. So
the גר Ger is a גר צדק Ger tzedek and, you know,
I don't know, somehow לעקר, Le-eker, I forget exactly but how we
exactly divide. But anyway, one of them is גר צדק. Ger tzedek.
Oh, it says או לגר תושב עמך או לעקר משפחת גר. O
le-ger toshav imcha o le-eker mishpachat ger. So גר Ger is גר
צדק, Ger tzedek, גר תושב Ger toshav is a גר תושב, Ger
toshav, עקר משפחת גר Eker mishpachat ger is the נכרי. Nochri. That
was just a warning about עבודת זרה Avodat zarah aspect. Right,
it's just going to show you how far away you're going to,
yeah, you know, what will, the fate that will befall you, that's
the מוסר Mussar way חז"ל Chazal read the פסוק, Pasuk, but here
the הלכה Halacha way is also saying that you could be sold
to a גר. Ger. It's got to be more painful, right, has
to work for the עכו"ם Akum and that's, oh. Well, the first
stage of going down is that you're sold like, you know, you
know, to, it's more stages removed from the immediate Jewish family. So
that's, okay. What happens if you're sold to a gentile and when
שמיטה Shmitta or יובל Yovel comes about?
Yeah,
you mean the whole idea that an עבד עברי Eved Ivri goes
free after seven years, right? I think that's only if you're sold
to a Jew, not if you're sold to a non-Jew, which also
speaks about how you're getting yourself in a real difficult, you know,
position. Because the גמרא Gemara says that it's, you know, או דודו
או בן דודו יגאלנו, o dodo o ven dodo yigalenu, right, that
you have to be redeemed by a—you have to get your freedom
bought for you. So, right, okay. So, גמרא Gemara says like this.
All right, so that's the גר. ger. He didn't understand. Now here's
the other thing he doesn't understand. Oh, but first we have to
finish spelling out the point here.
אמר מר, Amar Mar, ואין אשת הגר קונה עבד עברי. ve'ein eshet
hager kona eved Ivri. And an אשת הגר eshet hager can't purchase
an עבד עברי. eved Ivri. So we already discussed that a גר
ger really can, it's just that the laws are a little different.
So the גמרא Gemara says, לימא דלא כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל? Leima
d'lo k'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel? Let's say this restriction on the woman
is not like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל? Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel? דתניא,
Detanya, had a ברייתא: braita: אישה קונה שפחות ואינה קונה עבדים. Isha
kona shifachot ve'eina kona avadim.
A woman can purchase female slaves, but not male slaves. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, אף קונה עבדים. af
kona avadim. Can purchase male slaves. So yes, it does seem like
there's a debate: can a woman purchase male slaves? Now, the גמרא
Gemara says no. אפילו תימא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Afilu teima Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel. It could be רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel. ולא קשיא. V'lo kashya. כאן בעבד עברי כאן בעבד כנעני.
Kan b'eved Ivri kan b'eved Kena'ani. A woman can purchase non-Jewish male
slaves, not Jewish male slaves. So what's the difference? So the גמרא
Gemara says: עבד עברי צניע לה. Eved Ivri tznia lah. Because the
concern is that you have this male person under your control living
in the house, right? So that you—you know, it'll lead to sexual
impropriety. So the point is, ah, but if the guy's Jewish, you
figure that, you know, he'll be able to keep his mouth shut.
So therefore, it won't go publicized, I think. Okay? So therefore, we're
more concerned that something is going to go wrong because the guy
could be—will be more discreet. Whereas if it's non-Jewish, we're afraid he
won't keep his mouth shut, so it won't be discreet, so we're
not as afraid that something is going—is going to go wrong. עבד
כנעני פריץ ליה. Eved Kena'ani paritz leh. The עבד כנעני eved Kena'ani
won't be discreet and therefore there's less concern that something will go
wrong. You could also say that maybe the—maybe the non-Jew, maybe the
non-Jew
is seen as more, you know, foreign and therefore less likely to
be a, you know, a potential sexual partner. But anyway, but the
גמרא Gemara says the concern is less present in the case of
the non-Jew—of the non-Jew. Of course you could also say the non-Jew
is more subject, right? Is more fully owned, and therefore more, you
know, there's a greater power differential there. But the גמרא Gemara is
not concerned about it in the case of the non-Jew, only in
the case of the Jew. Right? And as I said, a Jewish
man can own female Jewish slaves, but that's only under בת מצוה,
bat mitzvah, so presumably we're not afraid of impropriety in that state.
Okay. גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא הא דתני רב יוסף, Ela
ha d'tani Rav Yosef, ארמלא לא תרבי
כלבא, Armala lo tarbi kalba, a widow should not raise a dog,
ולא תשרי בר בי רב באושפיזא, v'lo tishri bar bei rav b'ushpiza,
and she should not host
a—you know, a ישיבה yeshiva student in her inn. Because again, we're
afraid of either actual impropriety, or at least תוספות Tosafot says we're
not really afraid of impropriety with the dog, but we're at least
afraid of perception of impropriety. So the גמרא Gemara says: בשלמא בר
בי רב צניע ליה. Bishlama bar bei rav tznia leh. We understand
why there's a concern about the ישיבה yeshiva student, because that'll, you
know, because again, because he's discreet. So because if they were to
do something wrong, he would be discreet, we're concerned that it could
lead to something wrong, or perceptions of impropriety. אלא כלבא. Ela kalba.
But a dog? כיון דמסרך
בה. Keivan d'misrach bah. If she were actually to have been doing
some, you know, sexual things with the dog, the dog would be
like following after her. Okay? Is the גמרא's Gemara understanding. Okay? So
then it would be very public. So how could we—so why should
we be afraid? Obviously nothing is going wrong because people would see
the results of it. So the גמרא Gemara says: סוף מירססא. Sof
mirsasa. So she should be afraid. So ah, you know, you say:
כיון דכי שדיא ליה אומצא מסרך בה. Keivan d'ki shadya leh umtza
misrach bah. So there are other reasons a dog could follow you
around because you're always throwing it juicy pieces of meat. So therefore,
אמרי אינשי, amri inshi, so people will say: משום אומצא דשדיא ליה
הוא דמסרך. Mishum umtza d'shadya leh hu d'misrach. So it won't be
public. People will say, yeah, it's following her because she treats it
so nicely and she gives it juicy bones or whatever. But you
know, anyway, so we're afraid therefore that that could lead to improprieties
or תוספות Tosafot says perceptions of improprieties. Moving on. גר תושב אמרו
לו לעניין ריבית מאי? Ger Toshav amru lo l'inyan ribit mai? Now
I don't understand the meaning of the גר תושב Ger Toshav in
the ריבית ribit context. Why not?
דכתיב, Dechtiv, the פסוק pasuk says: וכי ימוך אחיך ומטה ידו עמך.
V'chi yamuch achicha umata yado imach. If your brother becomes poor and
his, you know, his hand falters,
והחזקת בו גר ותושב וחי
עמך. vehachazakta bo ger vetoshav vechai imach.
A resident alien and he should live with you. So this is
first of all the obligation to help sustain the life of a
גר תושב. Ger Toshav. Okay? Not only a גר צדק, Ger Tzedek,
even somebody that is just dwelling amongst you, or the way חז"ל
Chazal understand it, someone who accepted the שבע מצות בני נח. sheva
mitzvot bnei Noach. אל תקח מאתו נשך
ותרבית. Al tikach me'ito neshech v'tarbit. But then the פסוק pasuk ends
by saying, not only do you have to sustain them, but do
not take interest. So it sounds like you're not allowed to take
interest from a גר תושב. Ger Toshav. It says: גר ותושב עמך
אל תקח מאתו
נשך ותרבית, Ger vetoshav imach al tikach me'ito neshech v'tarbit, ויראת מאלוהיך
וחי אחיך עמך. v'yareta me'Elohecha vechai achicha imach. Okay, that's the פסוק.
pasuk. ורמינהי, Urreminhu, I'll ask you on this: לווין מהן ומלווין אותן
בריבית. Lovin mehen umalvin otan b'ribit. And this is why we did
because we quoted this ברייתא braita earlier. You can borrow from non-Jews
and lend to non-Jews with interest. וכן בגר תושב. V'chein b'Ger Toshav.
And also with a גר תושב Ger Toshav you can borrow and
lend in interest. How could you say that? The פסוק... pasuk... The
פסוק *pasuk* says don't charge a גר תושב *ger toshav* interest; it's
an explicit פסוק *pasuk*. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק *Amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak*, מי כתיב אל תקח מאיתם *mi ketiv al tikach mei-itam*?
It doesn't, first it says אחיך *achicha* and then it says גר
ותושב *ger v'toshav*. It doesn't say don't take from them, אל תקח
מאתו כתיב *al tikach meito ketiv*, don't take from him, מישראל *m'Yisrael*,
don't take from the Jew. So it says like if your fellow
becomes poor or a גר תושב *ger toshav* you should sustain them,
don't take from him נשך ותרבית *neshech
v'tarbit*. So the him now is referring not to the most proximate
case, the גר תושב *ger toshav*, but the first case. Don't take
from your fellow Jew, but yes you can take from the גר
תושב *ger toshav*. Okay, so that's a very interesting read of the
פסוק *pasuk*. פשט *Pshat* of the פסוקים *psukim* certainly should be indicating
otherwise. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*: אל תקח מאתו נשך ותרבית *Al tikach
meito neshech v'tarbit*, אבל אתה נעשה לו ערב *aval ata na’aseh lo
arev*. Yes, you cannot take interest from a non-Jew, but you can
be a guarantor, an ערב *arev*, for a non-Jewish loan, which basically
means like this: so
our friend Christopher here is wait, how would this work? Oh yes,
okay,
Eli here is going to lend
$1000 at 10% interest to our friend Christopher. Okay, and so he
needs a co-signer, so I agreed, so I'm allowed, I can't borrow
from Eli with interest, okay, but I can co-sign for a non-Jew
on a loan that's been lent with interest. The only problem is
if I'm now co-signing on that loan and the non-Jew defaults, Eli's
going to collect from me and I'm going to wind up having
paid essentially interest from a Jew to a Jew. It's a little
funny because I never borrowed the money to be seen as if
I'm paying, but one way to conceptualize an ערב *arev*, a co-signer,
is I will treat it as if you lent me the money.
Okay, that's one way of seeing what a co-signer is, right? I'm
also a borrower here. So if that's true and then Eli comes
to me, then I'm paying Eli for interest for a loan. So
that's the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* question. למאן *L'man*? אילימא ערב דישראל *Eileima arev
d'Yisrael*, now if you say that you can be a co-signer for
a Jew-to-Jew lent loan of interest, that's certainly not true. והתניא *V'hatanya*,
אלו עוברין בלא תעשה *eilu overin b'lo ta’aseh*, the following people transgress:
המלוה והלוה והערב והעדים *hamalveh v'haloveh v'ha'arev v'ha'edim*, anybody who's part of
the whole process, whether it's the borrower, the lender, the witness, or
the co-signer. So clearly you can't be a co-signer for a Jew,
אלא לנכרי *ela l'nochri*, you can be a co-signer for a non-Jew
who borrows with interest. And now the גמרא *Gemara* still doesn't like
it. וכיון דדינא דנכרי דאזיל בתר ערב *v'keivan d'dina d'nochri d'azil batar
arev*, since the law of the non-Jews is that the lender can
go first to the co-signer. If I co-signed for the non-Jew and
we were to be following non-Jewish law, Eli could come straight to
me. So if he can come straight to me, I really am
seen as the borrower in that case. So if that's true, איהו
ניהו דקשקיל מיניה ריביתא *ihu nihu d'kashkil minei ribita*, so basically Eli's
taking ריבית *ribbit* from me. It's like I borrowed the money and
I'm paying it to Eli, he forgets the non-Jew, he comes straight
to me, so how is that allowed? So אמר רב ששת *amar
Rav Sheshet*, שקיבל עליו לדון בדיני ישראל *shekibel alav ladun b'dinei Yisrael*.
No, we made an agreement that we were going to you know,
even though Eli lent the money to the non-Jew and I co-signed,
so there's Jews, non-Jews here, whatever, we said if this ever comes,
if we ever have to deal with this case, adjudicate it, we'll
adjudicate it in Jewish court. Now in Jewish court Eli has to
first go to the borrower himself before coming to me, and therefore
it's okay. Why? Since he goes to the borrower himself, it's not
considered like I lent money. He can only come to me if
the borrower defaults. If that's true, so let's say the guy borrowed
$1000, paying 10% interest, by now he owes $1500,
Eli comes to collect, he defaults, Eli comes to me. At this
stage Eli says you co-signed, pay me $1500.
At
that moment I owe him $1500. It never started that I initially
owed $1000 and now I'm paying an extra $500. No, because fundamentally
his relationship was with the borrower, and therefore the borrower was increasing
his debt, I was totally out of it. When the borrower now
has a debt of $1500 and he's defaulted and Eli comes to
me, my beginning of my relationship is a debt to Eli of
$1500, so it's not ריבית *ribbit*, right? I'm paying him more than
the loan but I never had the relationship of the loan, I
just owe him now the full amount. Okay, so that's how come
it can work. שקיבל עליו לדון בדיני ישראל *Shekibel alav ladun b'dinei
Yisrael*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, אי קיבל עליו לדון בדיני ישראל
ריבית נמי לא לישקול *ei kibel alav ladun b'dinei Yisrael ribbit nami
lo lishkol*? If he accepted to adjudicate in Jewish court, how do
we let him pay interest at all? Now I don't really get
that, but maybe somehow the גמרא *Gemara*, you know, what does that
mean? ריבית *Ribbit*, I mean is that going back to the earlier
גמרא *Gemara* that you're not supposed to lend non-Jews with interest? You
know, maybe it means that we wouldn't let you collect the increased
amounts from me because it was based on ריבית *ribbit*? Like I
don't really understand the question so much because it was allowed to
lend the non-Jew with interest. Anyway, the גמרא *Gemara* says, אמר רב
ששת שקיבל עליו לזה ולא קיבל עליו לזה *amar Rav Sheshet shekibel
alav lazeh v'lo kibel alav lazeh*. No, no, no, you agreed that
the interest part of the arrangement would be binding even if you
went to a Jewish court, and maybe the Jewish court didn't like
interest even with non-Jews,
but. So because he doesn't go initially to me, I can actually
wind up paying him a higher amount than the initial loan, because
I wasn't the borrower. You had a question Eli? It seems like
there's maybe you entered into some sort of connection as a guarantor
right from the beginning? Right. The question is how do we conceptualize
it. When I co-sign, is it like you're lending me the money
as well and you can collect from me? If that's true, then
I'm paying you interest. Or do we say no, the co-signing is,
if this person defaults, I promise to cover his debt to you?
So if that's true, I never paid, I never increased my debt
to you, there was never a basic debt that then the amount
increased. It's at the moment he defaults, that becomes my obligation to
you. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says let's take it a
little bit further. תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*. מלווה ישראל מעותיו של נכרי
מדעת הנכרי *Malveh Yisrael maosav shel nochri m'daas ha'nochri*.
A Jew can lend his money, can lend out the money of
the non-Jew with the awareness of the non-Jew. So what does this
mean? Let's take a look. תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*. מלווה ישראל מעותיו
של נכרי מדעת הנכרי אבל לא מדעת ישראל *Malveh Yisrael maosav shel
nochri m'daas ha'nochri aval lo m'daas Yisrael*. But not so he's lending
the money of a non-Jew with the awareness of the non-Jew, but
not only with the awareness of the Jew. What does that mean?
So thankfully, we're going to explain it. כיצד *Keitzad*. ישראל שלווה מעות
מן הנכרי בריבית *Yisrael she'lavah maos min ha'nochri b'ribbis*. Okay, I borrowed
money from Christopher with ריבית *ribbis* here. Okay, וביקש להחזירם לו *u'veikesh
l'hahazirum lo*. So I borrowed a thousand, now I owe fifteen hundred,
okay, and I'm taking my fifteen hundred to him. מצא ישראל אחר
*Matza Yisrael acher*. Now Eli bumps into me, ואמר לו *v'amar lo*,
and Eli says to me, you know what? Give me that fifteen
hundred dollars, ואני אעלה לך כדרך שאתה מעלה לו *va'ani a'aleh l'cha
k'derech she'attah ma'aleh lo*. And I'll continue to pay interest. So, you
know, you never paid back Christopher there. You still owe him the
money. But transfer the loan to me. But Christopher isn't agreeing to
it. So now you want that fifteen hundred dollars, you're going to
agree to pay interest, but the only way it's going to work
since Christopher hasn't been consulted is you're going to pay me the
interest and then I'm going to pay it to Christopher, right? So
that's not okay because you're paying me interest, right? So that's not
okay. ואני אעלה לך כדרך שאתה מעלה לו אסור *va'ani a'aleh l'cha
k'derech she'attah ma'aleh lo assur*. ואם העמידו אצל נכרי *V'im he'emido eitzel
nochri*. But let's say fine, let's go to Christopher. So they go
to Christopher and Eli says, you know what, fifteen hundred dollars, I'm
going to give it to Eli, I'm stepping out of this, now
it's between the two of you, and now you're going to pay
him the interest, that's okay. Okay, but the חידוש *chiddush* here is,
he didn't give you the fifteen hundred dollars. I gave you the
fifteen hundred dollars that was money that was supposed to go to
him, but in this context, it seemed like he's giving it to
you and it's your relationship to him and I'm out of it,
and therefore it's okay. וכן נכרי שלווה מעות מישראל *V'ken nochri she'lavah
maos mi'Yisrael*. How about the flip? Christopher borrowed money from me בריבית
*b'ribbis*. וביקש להחזירם לי *u'veikesh l'hahazirum li*. Now he's coming back to
me with the fifteen hundred, the thousand plus the five hundred of
interest payment. מצא ישראל אחר *Matza Yisrael acher*. Eli bumps into him
ואמר לו *v'amar lo*, תנם לי *t'neim li*, you know what, give
that money to me, ואני אעלה לך כדרך שאתה מעלה לו *va'ani
a'aleh l'cha k'derech she'attah ma'aleh lo*. I'll continue to pay you Christopher,
you'll continue to pay Dove. That's fine.
Your relationship was with the non-Jew, my relationship was with the non-Jew,
that's okay. מה עשה *Ma aso*? כדרך שאתה מעלה לו מותר *k'derech
she'attah ma'aleh lo muttar*. That's okay. ואם העמידו אצל ישראל *V'im he'emido
eitzel Yisrael*,
but if we all, you and Christopher come to me and say,
no no no, Christopher is now out of the picture, now I'm
going to continue with you. So now you're paying me ריבית *ribbis*.
ואם העמידו אצל ישראל אסור *V'im he'emido eitzel Yisrael assur*. It's forbidden.
Okay, so I guess what we'll do here is we'll unfortunately we'll
have to stop at this moment and we'll sort of continue to
unpack this, but this is going to be very interesting because initially
we dealt with how רבנו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* solved the whole problem
of lending to non-Jews at all with interest based on a גמרא
*Gemara*. This is going to be a major way in which Jews
found a huge loophole to lend to fellow Jews with interest. Can
people see what the way is?
Use the non-Jew as the middleman. Use the non-Jew as the cut-out,
right? So you know, so I lend to the non-Jew, the non-Jew
lends to you, ultimately, whatever, so that's going to be what we'll
discuss tomorrow.
Okay?